Guide to the Pierpont Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Pierpont Family Papers
1656-1885
MS 1125
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(2 boxes)
Correspondence, diaries, financial and legal papers, inventories, deeds, and accounts of members of the Pierpont family of North Haven, Connecticut. The principal figure is Daniel Pierpont, business man and town clerk of North Haven whose papers include an account book kept while building a house (1846), fourteen deeds for land in North Haven and a description of a churn invented by him. His diary (1824) contains an account of a murder trial in New Haven interrupted by the arrival of General Lafayette, and a description of a journey through southern New York state where he observed preparations for the reception of LaFayette. There is also an estate inventory for Hezekiah Pierpont (1792), financial papers of Rufus Pierpont and a resolution (Aug 1, 1855) of St. John's Church on his death.
Pierpont family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Mrs. E. Nesbit, 1949; gift of Mrs. Jordon T. Jack and Mrs. Ralph A. Winter, 1982.
Existence and Location of Copies
Papers relating to the genealogy of the Pierpont family are available on microfilm (97 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM144.
Related Materials
Pierpont's Store Collection, MS Group No. 399.
Arrangement
Arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
Papers of the Pierpont Family of North Haven, Conn., chiefly of Daniel Pierpont, 1775-1851, a business man and town clerk there for many years.
Daniel Pierpont's diary, Jan.-Aug. 1824, giving an account of a murder trial in New Haven which was interrupted by the arrival of General Lafayette on Aug. 21, 1824. Included also is a journal [inversed and reversed] of a journey, Sep. 2-18, 1824, with William Warner. In the course of the journey they traveled from North Haven to Oxford, N. Y., though southern New York state and returned by a different route; passing through Cairo, N. Y. where they observed throngs of people preparing for Lafayette's arrival.
Two letters, one a draft of a letter, from Daniel Pierpont to an unnamed person concerning the writer's claim to some land apparently in New York state in the vicinity of Montrose [noted as mailed Sep. 12, 1832] and the other, Dec. 30, 1841 is from Dennis Kimberly to Daniel Pierpont.
Fourteen deeds, 1806-1865, all to Daniel Pierpont and to land in North Haven, unless otherwise indicated, from the following: Jesse Andrews, May 2, 1811; Elbridge Gerry Blanchard, July 24, 1837 [also to Elias Pierpont]; Moses. T. Brockett, Nov. 6, 1820; Jonathan H. Dayton, Aug. 6, 1836; John Gill, May 17, 1830 [in Susquehanna County, Penn.]; Town of Hamden, Conn., Dec. 25, 1844 [signed by Leverett Hitchcock, treas.]; Albert E. Moulthrop, Nov. 5, 1845; Elias Pierpont, 1803-1883, to his sister, Harriet Pierpont 1808- ,June 10, 1856; Harriet R. Pierpont to Elias and Harriet Pierpont, June 8, 1865; Ruel Todd, [with his wife, Lucinda (Pierpont) Todd], Jan. 1, 1828 [in Hamden]; William Todd. Jr. Sep. 14, 1836 [a building in North Haven]; Isaac Tuttle, June 4, 9 [in Hamden], 1842; Edward Whedon, June 18, 1806 [in Branford].
The miscellaneous papers consist of 15 items, 1792-1885, and undated. They include: inventory, Sep. 10, 1792, of Land and livestock, labeled "Hezekiah Pierpont his Bill of Estate", indenture, Dec. 10, 1798, from Joshua Barnes and James Ives, binding Chancy Linds to Isaiah Brocket; selectior by the Proprietors of North Haven, at meeting Nov. 30. 1807, Daniel Pierpont clerk, of a Committee to petition the General Assemble at Hartford for permission to build a dyke across the New Haven East River; list, Aug. 29, 1809, by Daniel Pierpont, of stock tools and fine woods (mahogany, ect.), endorsed "When we first commenced business"; agreement, June 10, 1824, in the hand of Daniel Pierpont, between him, of the one part, and his brother, Ezra (1757-1842), Joseph (1760-1833), and Russell (1763-1844) Pierpont of the other part concerning the estate of their father Joseph Pierpont, 1730-1824, deposition, Aug. 21, 1828, of Abner Strong, in the case of the town of Canton vs. North Haven cause not specified [mutilated]; list of qualified electors chosen at a meeting of the selectmen of North Haven, Mar. 28, 1842; Daniel Pierpont's "Building Acts," being his record, Apr.-Sep. 1846, of materials, workmen, etc. on a house he was building with entries on weather and other matters [1 pocket account book]; bill, June 3, 1841 from Charles Durand to [Rufus Pierpont, 1818-1855] for dry goods; bill Sep. 20, 1847, from E. E. Huggins & Co. to Rufus Pierpont, for chinaware; resolutions; Aug. 1, 1855, of St. John's Church on the death of Rufus Pierpont; copy of writ and original complaint from the Justice's court, New Haven, June 18, 1885, by Edward L. Linsly, J. P. concerning the case of Whitney Elliott vs. Mrs. Harriet R. Pierpont, Elijah M. Beaumont and Gustavus Eliot; description of a churn invented by Daniel Pierpont, [undated]; list with valuations of his livestock and real estate [undated]; his Division of Debts etc. added & cast on his paper being one folder of figures with names and amounts and nature of business not indicated.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Estates (Law); Families; Inventions; Connecticut; New York (State) -- Description and travel; North Haven (Conn.); Account books; Deeds; Diaries; Dummer, Jeremiah, 1681-1739; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834; Pierpont, Daniel, 1775-1851; Pierpont, Elias, 1803-; Pierpont, Harriet, 1808-; Pierpont, Hez. B. (Hezekiah Beers), 1768-1838; Pierpont, James, -1938; Pierpont, John, 1785-1866; Pierpont, Rufus, 1818-1855; Pierpont family
- Inventory, 1792-1885; 0.25; (1 box)
  - General family papers
    - Deeds, 1806-1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Legal papers, 1798-1885 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hezekiah Pierpont
    - Estate inventory, 1792 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Daniel Pierpont
    - Correspondence, 1832, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Diary and journal, 1824 January-September (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Description of "Pierpont's Churn", Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Account book, with accounts for the building of a house, 1846 April-September (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Inventories and accounts, 1809, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rufus Pierpont
    - Resolutions of St. John's Church, North Haven, on his death, 1855 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bills, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Additional material, 1656-1792; Accession 1983-M-002; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Preliminary inventory by Lynn J. Stewart 1982 Aug
  Received from: Mrs. Jordan T. Jack and Mrs. Ralph A. Winter, 1982 Jul 14
  - Correspondence
    - ALS John Eaton to John Pierpont and a copy (reverse is extract of letter from Thomas Hill to John Pierpont, 1664 Apr 15), 1656 October 16, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ALS Thomas Hill to John Pierpont, 1664 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ALS Jeremiah Dummer, agent for Connecticut, in England, to Rev. James Pierpont, 1711 March 12, May 22, 1712 January (23?) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS Jeremiah Dummer to Rev. James Pierpont, 1713 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS Sir Richard Waller to Rev. James Pierpont, 1713 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS Rev. James Pierpont to Sir Richard Waller, 1714 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS Jeremiah Dummer to Rev. James Pierpont, 1714 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS James Pierpont, Y. 1718 (son of Rev. James Pierpont) to Jeremiah Dummer (fragment), 1721 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Jeremiah Dummer to James Pierpont, Y. 1718, 1722 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Drafts of letter from James Pierpont to the duke of Kingston, (one written on reverse of letter from Sam Royall to James Pierpont, 1725 Nov 13) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ALS Governor Talcott to James Pierpont, 1725 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Copy of James Pierpont to Henry Newman with copy of enclosure from James Pierpont to the duke of Kingston, 1726 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Copy of letter from James Pierpont to Evelyn, 2nd duke of Kingston, 1729 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS James Pierpont to Eliakim Palmer, with a copy of James Pierpont to the duke of Kingston, 1748 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Copy of James Pierpont to Eliakim Palmer with postscript to friends in Boston, 1748 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS Eliakim Palmer, agent for Connecticut in London, to James Pierpont, 1749 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS James Pierpont to the successor of E. Palmer as agent for Connecticut in London, 1749 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Extract of a letter from Dr. Gideon Wells to Rev. Partridge, re James Pierpont., 1750 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS James Pierpont to the president of Dartmouth College, re relationship to duke of Kingston, 1773 August 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 2 copies of that letter, one incomplete, 1789 March 6, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS Robert Pierpont, Jr. to Evelyn Pierpont and a copy of that letter, 1786 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - ALS Thomas Clarke to Hezekiah B. Pierpont, enclosing copies of birth and baptismal records for Rev. James Pierpont, 1792 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Genealogy
    - Deposition by Sarah Pierpont and by Shubel Seaver, John May and John Mayo, 1724 June 9, 11 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Deposition by Sarah Pierpont, 1725 September 3 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Certified copy of birth, marriage, death and baptismal records for family of Rev. James Pierpont, 1725 October 28-29 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Certified copies of birth and baptismal records for family of James Pierpont, 1774 January 14, 22, October 20, 21, 25 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Indenture to finance Evelyn Pierpont's claim to the title and estate of the duke of Kingston, 1784 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 18)